"Edge City"
(边城)
Another one coming down
我要再放一根下去
Hang on
先等一下
THE MASK
摩登大圣
I got those...
我弄到了...
concert tickets you wanted
你要的音乐会票
You're kidding!
真的呀？
For Friday night?
是周五晚的？
Stanley, this is great
太棒了，史丹利
What time do I pick you up?
我几点去接你？
Here's the thing
有个小状况
My best girlfriend is here and she'd die to go to this...
我的好友来了 她想去得要命
so could we get an extra ticket for her?
能不能帮她弄一张？
They're sold out. That means there's no more
票卖光了，  买不到了
I can't let her sit home all alone
但我不能把她丢在家里
I'll tell you what
我看这样吧
Go with your friend
你跟她去听
I couldn't do that
这怎么行呢
No, come on
没关系啦
Stanley, you are the nicest guy
史丹利，你真是盖世
Really, you are
真的，史丹利
- Isn't he the nicest guy? - The best
查理，你说对不对？ 顶尖好人
That was the most sickening display
她的脸皮比牛皮还厚
- I've ever seen. - I disagree
恶心透顶 我不同意
I'm wearing her down
我跟她慢慢磨
Buddy, you need a little change of pace
老兄，你该换换口味了
Tonight, I'll take you on a love safari
今晚我带你去猎艳
Deep into the darkest heart of the urban jungle
深入都市丛林最黑暗之心
Tell me more, bwana
说来听听，酋长
The Coco Bongo CIub. Hottest new joint in town
椰鼓夜总会 全城最红的新场子
Only the cr me de la cr me need apply
只有摩登凯子才准入场
- How do we get in? - Are you kidding?
我们算老几？ 你别漏气了
Leave it to me. Trust me, buddy
交给我，你就安啦
This will be the perfect...
我们要红遍全城
night on the town
就在今夜
Hold the phone
且慢
Killer at three o'clock
绝色美女在三点钟方向
Stand back and observe
你留守后方好好观察
Where do I open an account?
请问在哪办开户？
New accounts,right here
新开户就在这里
You're Iucky, I was on my way out--
你真幸运，我正要出差
Hold this for me, please?
帮我拿一下
I'll hold anything you want
要我拿一辈子都行
Can you help me?
你帮我办，好吗？
So...
那么？
what kind of account do you want?
你想开哪种户头？
Well, I'm not sure exactly. I'm just terrible with things like that
我也不确定 我对理财最外行
That's an interesting tie, Mister...
你的领带帅毙了
Ipkiss, Stanley Ipkiss
在下史丹利伊卜吉
Tina Carlyle, it's a pleasure
幸会，我叫婷娜
Pleasure's all mine
荣幸之至
May I?
可以用吗？
What?
用什么？
I'm such a mess
我像落汤鸡
Oh, of course
请用
That's what they're there for
本来就是给人用的
As I was saying, that tie...
见到你的领带
reminds me of those, what do you call it, ink blot tests
使我想起那种心理测验 “墨渍测验”
- A Rorschach test. - Right
罗夏发明的 对
It sort of looks like...
它看起来像...
a young woman riding bareback
骑无鞍马的妙龄女
Sort of...
例如那
Lady Godiva or something
裸体的伯爵夫人
Of course
是的
What do you see, Mr. Ipkiss?
你自己觉得呢？
I don't know
我不知道
Bright colors...
颜色很亮丽
It's a power tie
带给人权力感
Supposed to make you feel...
使人感觉...
powerful
更够力
Does it work?
你够力吗？
Now, how about that account?
好了，关于开户的事
We have...
我们有
several different plans
好几种户头
Savings
活期
Checking
支票
Savings and checking
活期加支票
Savings and CD's
活期加定存
Checking and CD's
支票加定存
Savings, checking and CD's. T-Bills
活期加支票、定存 国库券
Or we can throw your money in a big mattress
或干脆把钱挖洞藏起来
Now, I have some forms for you to fill out
你填一些表格吧
That's it, sweetheart. Now just a little bit to the right
很好，再向右一点点
Keep it down back there
你们小声一点
We'll try
是的
- What do you think? - Layout's not bad. But...
你觉得如何？ 格局还可以，但...
the motion detectors are a pain
警报器非常棘手
But you can pulI this off, right?
你搞得定吗？
You talking to the Doctor
我办事，你放心
I do have one question
但我有个疑问
Which is?
你说
What's Niko have to say about this?
尼哥有什么意见？
Nothing
没意见
- This isn't his grift. - Get real, man
他不搞抢银行 你多用些脑筋
Everything is his grift
他什么都搞
He owns you, he owns this cIub, he owns this whole stinking town
你是他的，夜总会也是 他的势力遍及全城
Things change
现在不同了
You mess with Niko, you end up taking a dirt nap
你惹他，只有死路一条
He's the only one who's napping...
不用脑筋的是他
and I'm about to give him a serious wake-up call
我要狠狠将他唤醒
But we need cash...
但我们需要钱
so first we take the bank...
所以先抢银行
then we take Niko...
再做掉尼哥
and then, my friend, school is out
然后我们就自由了
And this whole city is our playground
全城任我们放肆猖狂
Bub, watch where you're going!
走路不长眼睛！
Hang on, hang on!
马上来
Don't get your panties in a twist
你急着去投胎呀
What the hell is it?
这是什么歪哥？
I don't know...
我不知道
about seven hundred bucks, eh?
值七百元就对了
Now, what can I do for you, bub?
有何贵干，朋友？
I'm here for the Civic
我来领我的喜美
The brake drums are shot and you need a new transmission
刹车鼓损坏 整组传动要换
What?!
什么？
All I wanted was an oil change
我只是来换机油
Lucky we caught these problems before they caused serious trouble
我们及早发现问题 算你狗命够大
Sign right here, and press down hard
签名，用力写
- There's no price. - There will be
没写价钱 我们会写
I've no car. I need a car tonight
我今晚要用车呀
Bring around the loaner
把专车借给他
The loaner?
专车？
It's a classic
古董名车
Gals, meet my buddy Stanley Ipkiss
查理，我死党史丹利伊卜吉
Humungo in the banking business
银行巨子
- Not really. - Let's get in this joint
胡说 咱们进去吧
How you doing, buddy?
大块头，你好吗？
- It's Charlie! - How you doing?
我是查理呀 你好
- How you doing, my friend? - Long time no see
近来可好？ 好久不见
Good to see you
真是幸会
Come on, gals
娘儿们，走吧
See you on the inside
咱们里面见
This is a mistake
这是误会
You crossed the rope. Never cross the rope
好大狗胆，竟敢跨越绳子
- My friends are inside. - Lose him
我朋友在里面 扔出去
This isn't fair
这怎么可以
Watch it, I'm a bleeder
小心，我有血友病
Put me down now, or I am never coming back here
放下来 否则别想赚我的钱
Jeez
衰到家了
Mr. Ipkiss!
伊卜吉先生
Hi
嗨
Are you okay?
你还好吗？
Me?
我？
I'm great.
我好得很
Really good
好得不得了
I never felt better, really
我从未这么开心过
I'm just...
我只是...
catching some air
出来透透气
Your car, sir
先生，你的车
That's not my car
这不是我的车
It matches the ticket
是它没错
AIright...
好吧
I'll take it
给我就开
But I am very angry!
但我非常不满意！
Believe this?
你相信吗？
You drive in in a Porsche...
我开保时捷来的
Hey, Mister!
先生
Hold on!
撑住呀
I know CPR!
我会心肺复苏术
Hey, you!
喂！你！
What are you doing down there?
你在下面干什么？
I'm just looking for...
我正在找...
my mask!
我的面具
I got it
找到了
Do you have any idea what time it is?
你知道现在几点了？
Actually, no
我真的不知道
My new carpet!
我新铺的地毯！
Well ,this is coming right out of your security deposit
伊卜吉，我要扣你的押金
You know...
我告诉你...
What?
什么？
Nothing
没什么
Well, that's what you are, Ipkiss, a big nothing
空心大老倌，没出息！
Aren't you due at the lab to get your bolts tightened?
你这冷血的母僵尸！
I should have said that
我应该骂给她听见
Hey, you
你好呀
Milo!
麦乐
No jumping up allowed. It's against doggie ordinance
不许乱跳 要遵守狗民生活须知
What do you want?
你想干什么？
You want me to throw that?
要我掷飞盘？
I'm very tired
我累毙了
I'll throw it one time
我只丢一次
I won't throw it with you attached to it
你咬着我怎么丢
You ready?
好了吗？
Get it
接住
Ipkiss!
伊卜吉
Turn down those cartoons!
小声一点！
AIright, Mrs. Peenman!
好啦，平曼太太
Dr. Neuman, you say that everybody wears a mask?
您说人人都戴着面具！
That's correct
没错
We all wear masks, metaphorically speaking
戴面具是一种比喻
We suppress the id, our darkest desires...
我们压抑本我的深层欲望
and adopt a more socially acceptable image
装出社会能接受的形象
The book is "The Masks We Wear" by Dr. Arthur Neuman
纽曼博士大作 “我们的面具”
Thank you for being here
谢谢您接受访问
What's the matter with you?
你是怎么了？
What is it?
怎么了？
What are you looking for?
你在找什么？
You like this thing? You like it?
你喜欢这玩意？
"The Masks We Wear"
我们的面具
"That's correct
没错
We all wear masks, metaphorically speaking"
戴面具是一种比喻
Yeah, right
酷毙了！
Smoking!
我现在要出征
It's party time
派对时间到了
P-A-R-T-Y
派-对
Why? Because I gotta
为什么？因为我想要
MANAGER
(管理经理)
QUIET PLEASE
(请轻声)
Look, ma, I'm road kill!
我成了路上的扁尸
- Get out of the road! - I think he wants to communicate
别挡路！ 他想较量一下
squeeze me gently
(轻轻按我)
Hey, mister...
先生
you got the time?
现在几点？
As a matter of fact, I do, Cubbie!
大草包，我告诉你吧
Look at that!
你瞧瞧
Time to honk your nose and pulI your underwear over your head
你该把鼻子当喇叭按
Come on!
上呀
Step right up here, don't be shy!
放马过来，别害羞
Nobody likes...
皮衣混混
a bashful leather head
最惹人厌
Move it!
快呀！
For my first trick...
我第一个戏法
I'll do something for you, son
要献给你
We have a giraffe. There you go, son. Now get out of here, you bother me
长颈鹿给你 一边凉快去，别烦我
Now...
现在...
Sorry, wrong pocket
抱歉，掏错口袋
For you...
给你的是...
a little body English
用身体语言吧
A French poodle
法国贵宾犬
The dog was rabid, had to put it down
它有狂犬病，必须安乐死
At last but not least, my favorite
压轴的，是我的最爱
A Tommy gun
机关枪一支
This is incredible
真想不到
With these powers I could be...
有了一身特异功能
a superhero
狗熊都能变英雄
I'd fight crime, protect the innocent...
挑战犯罪，保护无辜
work for world peace
维护世界和平
But first...
但首先
RIPLEY'S AUTO FINISHING
去报仇
Hold onto your Iug nuts...
做好心理准备
it's time for an overhaul
接受彻底翻修吧
It was a dream
这是一场梦
I must lay off the cartoons
我该戒掉卡通了
Lt. Kellaway. You know anything about the disturbance last night?
我是凯拉威分队长 你知道昨晚的骚动吗？
Disturbance?
骚动？
Some prowler broke in and attacked Mrs. Peenman
歹徒闯入，攻击平曼太太
Attacked?
攻击？
You didn't hear anything?
你都没听见？
She unloaded a couple of rounds of buckshot 5 feet from here
她在你门外 发射好几枚霰弹
Look at the floor
看地上
He put that right in my floor, then he jumped out...
他把钟放下，跳出窗外
the window. Officer, are you writing notes?
你记下来没有？
This is...
这真是...
impossible
诡异
Those pyjamas are impossible. This happened
真有其事 你的睡衣才诡异
See, I have...
我
an inner ear problem
内耳有问题
- Sometimes I can't hear anything. - Is that so?
有时候全聋 真的吗？
Here's my card. If you recall anything unusual about last night...
名片给你.你若想起昨晚的事
anything at all, call me
只要记起来，就通知我
You bet. Thank you
没问题，谢谢
And good Iuck...
祝你好运
cracking the case
顺利破案
Oh, my God, I'm late!
天哪，迟到了
Keys, keys...
钥匙呢
Where's the keys?
钥匙在哪儿？
Damn
讨厌
Get the keys
麦乐，去找钥匙
Find them
叨给我
I am so late
晚得太离谱了
Good boy
好狗儿
Come on, Milo. Give them to me. Drop it
给我吧 松口呀
I want a proctologist standing by
找肛门医生待命
The best one you can find
找第一把肛门交椅
Can you tell me what happened?
我是记者，请问案情？
- No, you can quote me. - Looks like some Mob tactic
我说了你会乱写 好像是黑道仇杀
She broke the case. Come on, get these rubbernecks out of here
她已经破案了呢 把闲杂人等赶走
Where were you last night? We looked all over for you
昨晚你在哪儿？ 找你找破了头
Did you happen to look outside, in the gutter?
你有去臭水沟里找吗？
Did you check the paper?
你有没有看报？
Your girlfriend got a great review
你的马子上了头版
Bombshell Explodes at Coco Bongo
“肉弹爆破椰鼓”
You're 50 minutes late. That's like stealing
迟到五十分 如同偷我的薪水
I'm sorry, Mr. Dickey. It'll never happen again. I've been a jerk
对不起，以后不敢了 我真是窝囊废
If you weren't busy oogling girlie pictures...
你如果少看些裸女
you might get some work done
就能多办些公事
Sir. She's a perspective client of Stanley's
她可能成为史丹利的客户
Really?
真的吗？
The next time she comes in...
如果她再光临
send her to my office
请她到我办公室
You bet
没问题
Gee, I wish "my" daddy owned a bank
但愿我爸是银行老板
Then I could be a rich little creep too
我就能跟他一样臭屁
You think she'll ever come back?
她还会来吗？
Oh, man, forget her. Listen to me
别提她了.你听我的话
Girls like her always look for the BBD: Bigger Better Deal
她那种妞心中想的就是钓凯子
You don't know that
你不了解她
She's an artist. She's...
她是艺术家，她.
- sensitive. - Forget her
感觉敏锐 忘掉她吧
She'll rip out your heart, put it in a blender and hit "frappe"
她会扯烂你的心 打成果汁喝
You don't need her. You need somebody down to earth
你需要的是单纯的那一型
Somebody with some integrity. Somebody with...
正派的女子
red hair...
有着一头红发
fulI, pouting lips...
噘着丰满的唇
a white blouse, green jacket...
白衫，绿外套
and a name tag
戴识别证
You really narrowed it down
这范围太小了
Too bad she's already taken
可惜被我包了
Hello there, may I be of assistance?
你好，请问有何贵干？
Stanley Ipkiss?
你是史丹利伊卜吉？
Hi! I'm Peggy Brandt from the Tribune
我叫佩姬，论坛报来的
I canceled my subscription because they kept stealing--
我没续订你的报是因为
No, actually, I want to ask you a few questions
我是有事问你才来的
Really? About what?
真的吗？什么事？
Ripley Auto Finishing. You're a customer, aren't you?
你是那修车厂的客户吗？
Me?
我？不是
I don't even have a car
我根本没车
You know, 'cause they pollute
因为车辆会污染环境
You don't own an '89 Civic?
你有一辆八九年的喜美？
Oh, that car, yeah
你说那一辆呀
It's coming back to me
我想起来了
Miss... What was your name?
请问芳名？
Peggy Brandt
佩姬布兰
Wait a minute
且慢
Peggy Brandt?
你是佩姬布兰？
Of "Ask Peggy"?
那位专栏作家？
That's right
没错
You printed one of my letters last year
去年你登出我的信
Remember? "Nice Guys Finish Last."
“好男人永难出头”
You're Mister Nice Guy?
你就是那位好男人？
Do you realize how much mail we got about that letter?
无数读者写信到报社问你
100's of women are looking for a guy like you
几百位女子想找你这种人
Really?
真的吗？
You know how hard it is to find a decent man in this town?
你知道好男人 有多难找吗？
Most think monogamy is a kind of wood
多数男人都是大色鬼
Why are you covering this story?
你为何采访这案子？
Because "Dear Peggy" pays dick. I'm starving to death
写专栏酬劳低，快饿死了
I'm looking to become a real reporter
我想当真正的记者
When you were at Ripley Auto did you see anything suspicious?
你在修车厂 有看到可疑的事吗？
Anything?
任何怪事？
I won't make trouble for you
我不会给你惹麻烦
I just want the truth
我只要查明真相
God, I wish I knew the truth. You know, I really do
但愿我知道真相 我真的希望
If you think of anything...
如果你想起来
this is my number
就通知我
This is my...
这支电话...
you know, personal number
是我的专线
100's of women are looking for a guy like me?
真的有几百位女子 想找我？
Sure
当然了
I'm one of them
包括我在内
120 yards
一百二十码
Hello, Dorian
你好，多利安
Thanks for dropping by
感谢你光临
Next time, call. Leave the delivery boys at home
下次先打电话 别劳动你的狗腿子
The cops...
今天早上
tried to shut the cIub down this morning
警察想查封夜总会
They say you've been using the place to run your own small-time scams
警方说你用它掩饰犯罪
When I hear things like that...
当我听到此事
I start losing my concentration
我开始分心了
My game...
这一杆...
it goes straight to hell
万一打烂了
You could too
你也会被打烂
205 yards
二0五码
I'm fed up with you...
我受够你了
but....
但.
I'll cut you a break
我法外施恩
One week to get out of town
给你一周滚出城
After that...
如果你不滚
I'll use your empty little skulI to break in my new nine iron
我就用铁杆敲你脑袋
Are you okay?
你没事吧？
Your car, sir
先生，你的车
I am now
见到你就没事了
Tina, come on
婷娜，别这样
You can't
别这样
Go on
痒死了
I don't believe it
春梦醒得真快
Stupid
我太痴心了
She would never...
她会爱我才怪
No way!
不行
Hold on, Sugar
等一下，蜜糖
Daddy's got a sweet tooth tonight
大爷今夜想吃甜食
Somebody,stop me
打遍天下无敌手
Can't make the scene if you don't have the green
没钱就别想耍帅
I better make a little stop
我最好去捞一票
EDGE CITY POWER "SERVICE WORTH WAITING FOR"
(边城电力公司)
How's it going, Freeze?
怎样了，傅立兹？
It's looking good here
看来一帆风顺
You're on your own. I must go downstairs, make sure I'm seen
你们要靠自己了 我必须下楼让人看见
Do it
你去吧
The doctor is about to operate
傅立兹要出马了
Sorry, fellas. Waste not, want not
抱歉，各位 吃多少，拿多少
Cops!
条子！
Not on the list, not in the cIub
不在名单上，就不准入内
How do?
大家好
You on the list?
你在名单上吗？
No, but I believe my friends are. Perhaps you know them?
不，但你想必认识我朋友
Franklin, Grant...
蒋中正，孙中山
and Jackson
就是钞票啦
That's it! No one gets in
谁都不许进来！
Now we present the most beautiful flower of the Congo Bongo...
本店最美艳的花朵
Miss Tina Carlyle
婷娜小姐
Beautiful
美呆了
- Why are you here? - There's trouble
你来干什么？ 大势不妙
You better come upstairs
最好上楼说
Come on, let's go
我们走
Let's rock this joint
咱们来大闹天宫！
Smoking
乐歪了！
What happened?
怎么回事？
Someone hit the joint before us
有人抢先一步
Get that, Doc
来
Suck on that
哈一管
Son of a bitch!
天嫉英才呀
Who did this, man?
是谁干的？
Who?!
是谁？
Him!
他
That's the guy
就是他
The guy dancing with Tina?
婷娜的舞伴？
He's dead meat
他死定了
Come on
来
I want this place cleared now
马上给我清场
CIub's closed. Move it! You think I'm joking? Come on, move it!
打烊了，快走 不滚就试试看
Party's over, let's go!
派对结束了，走吧！
Get out of here
婷娜，你走开
Get lost!
滚一边去！
Okay, Twinkle Toes
摩登舞王，你听着
Where is my money, tell me now
你马上告诉我钱在哪？
You've got 17.5% in T-bills amortized over the fiscal year
你买国库券领利息
8% in stocks and bonds
还买股票和债券
Carry the 9, divide by the GNP...
除以国民生产毛额
Fortunately, funeral bouquets are deductible
还好，你的葬礼花圈免税
Ice this deadbeat
干掉这活宝
Shoot him!
干掉他！
Thanks
谢谢
You got me, partner
你打中我了
Hold me close,Red
抱紧我
It's getting dark
我眼前一片黑
Tell Auntie Em to let OId Yeller out
请阿姨别忘带老黄狗散步
Tell Tiny Tim I won't be coming home this Christmas
耶诞节我不回家过了
Tell Scarlet I do give a damn
乱世佳人，其实我受你
Pardon me
失礼了
Thank you
感谢捧场
You love me
观众爱我
You really love me
你们真的爱我
You're not going anywhere
你别想溜
Drop it, Tyrel!
枪放下
Drop it
放下
You got a warrant? Or did you come for a nightcap?
有搜索票吗？还是想喝酒？
What I got is probable cause
我手上有合理根据
Your boys knocked over Edge City Bank
你的手下抢银行
Easy. You're giving me a woody
别乱摸，好痒
And one was wearing a big, green mask
其中一人戴着大绿面具
For once, you're right
你难得说对一次
Except it wasn't one of my boys
但他不是我手下
Maybe if you tried a little actual police work...
你该确实查清楚才说
Cuff him
铐住他
We got a stiff upstairs. It's a guy from the heist
分队长，楼上有尸体 他是抢匪
Call that high-priced lawyer of yours
请你那高薪律师来
We'll go downtown for a chat
咱们去警局聊聊
Get him out of here
带走！
I know you're in there
伊卜吉，我知道你在家
Police!
我是警察
Open up!
开门
Oh, my God
妈祖娘娘呀
I know you're in there!
我知道你在里面
Open up!
开门
Come on, I'm getting blisters on my fingers
我敲得手起水泡了
Stop it
不可以
I'm coming, okay
别这样，我来了
I'll be right there
马上就来
Let's go, move it!
快一点
AIright!
好啦
Hi, Lieutenant
你好，分队长
This isn't the best time right now. I just--
现在我不方便
Won't you come in?
那请进吧！
Where were you last night?
你昨晚在哪里？
Here, mostly
差不多都在家
Something wrong?
出了事吗？
What do you know about The Mask?
你对面具怪客了解多少？
"Mask?"
面具怪客？
Don't insult my intelligence
别给我装蒜
He robs the bank you work in, then I find this in the Coco Bongo
他抢你的银行 我在椰鼓找到碎布
There can't be 2 idiots with these pajamas
这种骚睡衣只有你才有
May I see those pajamas?
我想看看你的睡衣
Those pajamas?
睡衣！
Those pajamas...
那些睡衣...
were stolen
被偷了
Somebody stole your pajamas?
睡衣会被人偷？
What is this city coming to...
这个城市有够堕落的
when a man's pajama drawer is no longer safe!
男人的睡衣都有人偷
Look at that guy
你看他
- Nobody's that fast at my bank. - I'll say
但愿我的员工有这么勤快 彼此彼此
That's one hell of a rubber mask
那橡皮面具真不赖
Lab reports?
化验室怎么说？
We got fingerprints from currency, but nothing matches Tyrel's men
钞票上有指纹，但不是多利安手下
He beat them to the punch
面具怪客比他们快
Get the bank employee files and run down the prints on a guy named Ipkiss
查银行员工档案，核对伊卜吉的指纹
You figure it was an inside job?
你认为有内贼？
I need some prints to lock this whack job up till doomsday
找到指纹 我就能关他一辈子
50 grand...
我悬赏五万元
to whoever finds that green bastard before the cops
看谁比条子 先找到面具怪客
I want you to get the word out to every street hustler...
你们把话放出去
every low life in this town. Understand?
传给边城每个混混和无赖
I want him here tomorrow, alive
明天把他抓来，要活的
You still here?
你们还等什么？
Come on, let's go
快去干活！
What are you looking at?
你看什么？
You
你
You're losing it
乱掉方寸了
I'm not losing anything...
我什么都没掉
except maybe some extra baggage
我只想甩掉一些累赘
What's that mean?
什么意思？
You didn't fight much last night when that freak kissed you
昨晚他吻你，你没有反抗
Did it look like I had much of a choice?
我反抗也没用呀
Maybe you did...
不见得吧
maybe you didn't. Who knows, right?
也许是没用，反正天知道
I'll tell you one thing
我告诉你
It's going to be payback for anybody who crosses me
谁惹毛我，我就找谁算帐
We have a crisis here and you stroll in an hour late?
银行出事 你还迟到一小时
If I must put up with--
我受够你这没路用的...
Back off, monkey boy...
滚你的，小金牛！
or I'll tell your dad you treat this place like your piggy bank
小心我向你老爸告状
Or we should call the IRS...
或是通知国税局
and arrange a vacation for you at CIub Fed?
请你去调查局度假！
That'll be all
走着瞧
Genius
大圣人呀
That was genius. Buddy, I have chills
你令我乐到心坎里
God! What side of whose bed did you wake up on, man?
你今天嗑了什么魔药？
I'm not sure
我也不清楚
I haven't exactly been myself lately
我最近不大像自己
You don't look real fabulous
你的气色不佳
Really, do I look bad?
真的吗？
Don't worry. This'll put the color back in your cheeks
安啦，这会使你恢复神采
2 tickets to the charity ball at the Coco Bongo CIub, Saturday
椰鼓办慈善舞会，周六晚
Anybody who's anybody will be there
大人物都将到场
Want to be my date?
陪我去吧？
Wait just a minute
先等一下
- Why are you here? - I wanted to thank you
你怎么来了？ 我来向你道谢
I don't have much to open an account with anymore
我没钱开户了
What about the cIub? You were doing great
你在夜总会很红呀
It's not your problem. I'll be okay
别为我操心，没事的
Come here
跟我来
You didn't stop by just to see me, did you?
你不只是来看我吧？
It's okay, tell me
没关系，告诉我
The guy they say robbed this place...
那个抢银行的人
- The Mask? - I think he was at the cIub
面具怪客？ 他去过夜总会
Really?
真的？
They say he's pretty...
听说他长得...
weird looking
有够怪异
Yeah, but...
不过...
you should see him dance
他是舞林豪杰
Did anyone find out who he is?
他到底是何方神圣？
Why, you interested?
你有兴趣吗？
Just curious, I guess
我只是好奇
I better be going
我该走了
Thanks for everything
谢谢你一番心意
You'd like to see him again?
你想再见到他，对不对？
I wouldn't mind
那就麻烦你了
I know him, you know
我认识他
You do?
真的？
We're old college buddies, him and me
我们是大学同窗
It's funny you mention he dances because...
你提到他的舞技
I taught him a couple of dance moves myself
有些舞步是我教他的
Think you could have him meet me tonight?
我今晚能见到他吗？
Maybe I could work something out
我想办法
- How about at Landfill Park? - Sunset
在公园好吗？ 日落时分
- Perfect. - Super
太好了
Thanks, Stanley. You really are a nice guy
谢了，你真是大好人
This is an interesting place
这玩意很有意思
Looks like fourth- or fifth-century Scandinavian
像四、五世纪的北欧面具
Possibly a representation of one of the Norse night gods, maybe Loki
可能是北欧的一位夜神 也许是洛基
Loki?
洛基？
Who is Loki?
洛基是谁？
The Norse god of mischief
北欧的恶作剧之神
Supposedly he caused such trouble that Odin banished him from Valhalla forever
他是闯祸大王 天父将他永远逐出天宫
Then he could have banished him into that mask
也许他被贬到面具里
I'm talking about mythology, Mr. Ipkiss
那都是神话
This is a piece of wood
这只是一块木头
but your book...!
但你的书...
My book is about masks as a metaphor
我的书是拿面具做比喻
A metaphor,not to be taken literally
不是照字面去解释
You suffer from a mild delusion
你患了轻微的妄想症
AIright
好吧
I'll prove it to you
我证明给你看
But I am not responsible for the consequences
但后果我不负责
Just sit back and enjoy the ride, Mr. Expert
坐下来欣赏吧，大专家
You don't scare me. Go right ahead
有啥好怕的，请便
See you
再见
You said Loki was a night god. Maybe it works at night
洛基是夜神 也许晚上才有效
I should warn you that I don't work personally with really sick people
先生，我警告你 我不亲自辅导重症患者
There are private institutions for those things
你该去找私人机构
I can arrange for a safe environment for you tonight, if you want
如果你想入院，我今晚就能帮你安排
I must see Tina
我一定要见婷娜
But what can I do?
但我该怎么办？
Do I go as myself...
以原来面貌去？
or The Mask?
或是戴上面具？
If I tell you, you promise to leave my office right now?
我说完，你就离开好吗？
Go as yourself...
本貌
and as The Mask
和面具一起去
Because they are both one and the same beautiful person
他们是一体的 都是大好人
Got the cross-check on the fingerprints. It's Ipkiss
指纹证实是伊卜吉的
I'm looking at him
我正盯着他
Keep the SWAT team standing by
叫霹雳小组待命
If he's half as bad as they say, we'll have a fulI dance card
若他真那么难缠 就得闹一夜
Pickle relish?
有泡菜酱吗？
- Get in the car. - But I ordered onion rings
上车 我还点了洋葱圈
What are you doing here?
史丹利，你怎么来了？
I wanted to make sure that you 2 got together all right
我只是路过来确定你们见到面
That's nice
你真好
I hardly ever stop by here
我很少来这里
It's hard to believe it was...
真想不到这里曾是...
a garbage heap
垃圾场
It's really beautiful right around sunset
日落时分真美
The methane emissions really pick up the colors
沼气加深了天色
All those...
满天的...
pinks and greens
姹绿嫣红
My friend will be along here any minute. I better go
他随时会到，我走了
Stanley, wait
等等，史丹利
Hello, cherie
你好，心肝儿
We meet again!
我们重逢了
Is it fate?
这是命运吗？
Is it meant to be? It is written in the stars...
是否星辰上面写着
that we are destined to fraternize?
我们注定要相好？
I'd like to think so
我愿意这样想
Kiss me, my dear, and I will reveal my croissant
吻我，我就奉献给你
I will spread your p t . I will dip my ladle in your vichyssoise
我带你同奔极乐 我带你共浴瑶池
She's so coy
她可真怕羞
I love it
我喜欢
Our love is like a red, red rose
我们的爱像红红的玫瑰
And I am a little thorny
令我兴奋莫名
Je t'adore! Je t'adore!
我爱慕你
Shoot the window. I don't care!
说法文比较不恶心
This is Kellaway. I need back-up
我是凯拉威，加派人手来
Cigarette?
抽烟吗？不抽？
Now, like Napoleon...
我好像拿破仑
I will divide and conquer
分散敌军，各个击破
Police!
我是警察！
Merde
电灯泡
Freeze
“别动”
Put your hands up
手举起来
But you told me to freeze
你不是叫我“结冻”？
AIright, alright, unfreeze
好啦，化冻
You're under arrest
你被捕了
It wasn't me
不是我干的
It was the one-armed man
是“绝命追杀令”那独臂人
AIright, I confess
好吧，我招了
I did it, you hear? And I'm glad, glad, I tell you!
是我干的，我非常得意
What are they going to do to me, Sarge? What are they going to do?
警伯，他们会把我怎样？
Sorry, son, that's not my department
抱歉，不关我的事
Search him
搜身
Where's a camcorder when you need one?
应该拍下来告你们刑求
It's going to be a long night. My wife'll kill me
今晚搞不完了 老婆会宰了我
- What is it? - Cops got Ipkiss at Landfill Park
怎么了？ 伊卜吉在公园被捕
Let me cover it. I need this story. You go home to Claire
让我去采访这案子 你回家陪老婆
I don't know. Ramsey said--
可是上面说...
I will take care of Ramsey
我去跟上面说
Thanks a million, I owe you one
感激不尽，算我欠你
Really big sunglasses, nerf ball...
超大墨镜
Bike horn...
单车喇叭
Small-mouthed bass... bowling pin...
小嘴鲈鱼
mouse-trap...
捕鼠器
rubber chicken...
橡皮鸡
- Little to the left. That's it. - I don't know
吃这个也痒，吃那个也痒
Funny eyeball glasses...
玩具眼珠
I've never seen those in my life
没看过这种眼镜
- bazooka. - I have a permit for that
火箭筒 我有执照的
- Picture of Kellaway's wife... - What?
凯拉威夫人玉照
CalL ME LOVER!
“爱人，我等你”
Margaret! Son of a bitch!
你勾引我老婆！
I figured you had a sense of humor
我还以为你幽默
you married her!
毕竟...夫妻一场嘛
That's got to hurt
这够痛了吧
Get him!
抓住他
It's over. Raise your hands...
伊卜吉，把手举起来
or we'll fire
否则开火
Hit it!
开枪
They call me Cuban Pete I'm the king of the rumba beat
人家叫我古巴皮 我是伦巴舞皇帝
When I play the maracas
当我摇起响葫芦
I go chick-chicky boom
我就劈哩啪啦碰
Yes, I'm Cuban Pete
是的，吾乃古巴皮
I'm the craze of my street
人间就属我最皮
When I start to dance everything goes Chick-chicky boom, chick-chicky boom
当我跳起舞，劈哩啪啦碰
The seoritas sing...
妞儿唱歌...
and they swing
又跳舞
It's very nice
跳得又帅又惹火
FulI of spice
跳得人心痒难熬
They dance and bring a happy ring Never a care
她们唱歌又跳舞 跳的真不错
Singing a song All the day long
从早到晚，笙歌不辍
If you like the beat Take a lesson from Cuban Pete
若你喜欢这节奏 就来学我古巴皮
I'll teach you to chick-chicky boom
脸贴着脸黏巴达
He's a modest guy
他这男人真内向
AIthough he's the hottest guy
不过却是万人迷
In Havana
哈瓦那的万人迷
Si, senorita, I know...
是的，小姐，我知道
It's very nice so fulI of spice
我是又帅又惹火
I place my hand on your hip
我把手放你身上
And if you will give me your hand
让你赏我几耳光
Then we shall try Just you and I
那么你我就起舞
- Not bad. - Shut up and help me down
热情有劲 闭嘴，拉我一把
I'll teach you to chick-chicky boom Chick-chicky boom
我会教你跳这支舞
Dance and I'll blow your brains out
再跳就轰掉你的狗头
Give me that thing
枪给我
See you!
后会有期
There! Let's get him. Snap out of it. This dance is over!
去抓他 醒过来，别跳了！
Let's go! Follow me, officers!
走呀，同志们
He's down the alley. Follow me. Come on. Grab your gun
他在巷子里 拿着枪跟我来
Stanley, get in!
史丹利，上车
There!
在那边
Halt, or I'll shoot!
再跑就开枪
Shoot! Shoot!
开枪呀
Seat belts
不绑安全带会罚款
I missed him
我没打中
Come on, we all missed him
谁打得中他
THE MASK ROBS BANK
“面具怪客抢银行”
I saw it
我看到了
I saw everything
全都看到了
What's happening to you, Stanley?
史丹利，你是怎么了？
It's crazy
我发疯了
I'm losing control
我无法控制自己
When I put that mask on...
当我戴上面具
I can do anything
我就能做任何事
Be anything
变成任何东西
It's wrecking my life
它毁灭着我
My life is wrecked. Wrecked
害我过得一塌糊涂
I don't know what's happening to you...
这些我并不清楚
but I do know this:
但我明白一点
that letter you sent my column...
写信到我专栏的那人
that was from a guy with more guts...
他的勇气十足
and more heart...
心地善良
than any of the creeps I've met in this city
强过全城所有的烂男人
Whatever that mask is...
不管那是什么面具
you don't need it
你都不需要了
You...
你
Stanley Ipkiss...
史丹利伊卜吉
are already all you'll ever need to be
你只需做好你自己
Gosh, Peg...
佩姬
do you really mean that?
这是你的真心话吗？
Actually...
老实说...
no
不见得
What?
什么？
Where were you? I've been vamping for 20 minutes
你们害我 多扯二十分钟的谎
Is this him?
就是他？
You got the 50 thou'?
五万块呢？
Give her the money
把钱给她
Right
很好
With the mask on, he turns into that green thing
他戴上面具就变成怪客
What are you doing?
你这是干什么？
Sorry. You really are a great guy, I just can't lose my condo
抱歉，你的确是好人 但我缺钱就没房子住
It's so hard to find an apartment in this city
在市内找房子太难了
You said you wouldn't hurt him!
你说过不会伤害他
I lied
我骗你的
Tell me
告诉我
How's this mask work?
面具有什么奇效？
I don't know. You just...
我也不清楚
put it on
你戴上就知道
Boss...
老板
be careful, huh?
保重呀
What a rush
酷得歪七扭八
You okay?
你还好吗？
I'm better than ever, you idiot
我从未这么好过
What do we do with Ipkiss?
怎样处置伊卜吉？
The police want the mask
警方要面具
We'll give them The Mask
就把面具怪客送警
The money better be here...
最好找得到钱
or you can Ip-kiss your ass good-bye
否则你就是夭寿怪客
Get over there
在这里
Can't believe it. Hardened cops dancing in the street...
想不到 干练警员沿街起舞
and broadcast on the 11 o'clock news
在夜间新闻播出
- The SWAT team was offered Vegas. - I'm history
赌城还请霹雳小组去作秀 我完了
The Captain'll have my badge for breakfast with a pension on top
队长会炒我鱿鱼 退休金泡汤
It's not all your fault. Something will turn up
这不能怪你 吉人自有天相
Sure, Ipkiss will fall right into my lap
除非伊卜吉掉在我怀里
Get him off of me!
把他弄开！
Wait!
等等
I can explain everything
让我解释清楚
You can explain everything? Explain this!
是吗？那你解释这个
Get him up! Let's go! I got a cell for you, pal
铐起来 我为你准备了客房
Forget about me, buddy
忘了我吧
Find a new place to live
找一个新窝
I'll be in here for a long, long time
我要关好久好久
You, with the face
喂，丑八怪
You got a visitor
有访客
- Why? - Is it true?
你怎么来了？ 是真的吗？
You're The Mask
你就是面具怪客
Yeah, but don't tell anybody. If I get...
别跟任何人说
a good lawyer and a deal...
只要找到好律师
I'll be out in about 10,000 years
我再关一万年就可以出狱
It's risky, coming here
你来这里太危险
Your boyfriend might be upset
你男友会不爽的
He'll be at the charity ball tonight
他今晚要去慈善舞会做坏事
Like what? The Lambada?
他想跳黏巴达吗？
This is serious. There must be a way to stop him
别耍嘴皮了，一定要阻止他
How does it work?
它有什么魔力？
I don't know
我不知道
It's like...
好像是...
it brings your innermost desires to life
它使人最隐密的欲望成真
If deep down inside...
若你的内心深处
you're a bit repressed and hopelessly romantic...
略带压抑却又浪漫至情
you become some sort of...
那你就会变成
a love-crazy wild man
为爱痴狂的浪人
And if you're like Dorian?
如果是多利安戴它呢？
Then we're all in big trouble
那大家都完了
And if I were you, I'd get out of town. Fast
若我是你 就马上远走高飞
Thanks
感谢你
For what?
谢什么？
Lots of things
很多事
Sharing a sunset with me
你与我分享夕阳
For being the only guy who treated me like a person, not...
只有你把我当人看
a party favor
而非当玩物
For being any kind of romantic...
感谢你一片深情
even a hopeless one
虽然浪漫得无药可救
You're welcome
不客气
That night at the cIub I knew...
那晚在夜总会
I'd found someone special
我邂逅了意中人
The Mask
面具怪客
It was the guy inside The Mask
不，是面具后面的男子
It was you all along
就是你本人
Lady, time's up
小姐，时间到
Could I have just...
拜托宽限...
one more minute?
一分钟？
I've got to disappear for a while now
我要躲藏一阵子
Don't know where but I'll let you know as soon as I can
我找到地方 会尽快通知你
Somebody help me!
救命呀
Guard, guard!
警卫
A woman's being chased in the alley
有人在巷内追杀女子
She needs help
快去救她呀
Sure. Keep it down
罗嗦，小声一点
Serve and protect, man!
你算什么人民保姆！
Good boy. Come on
好孩子，来
Jump up. Can you jump up?
跳上来，会吗？
Remember how I taught you not to jump up on people? Forget that
我曾教你别乱跳 现在收回成命
Come on! Get up here
跳上来
Get up. Get up here!
上来呀
Get up. Get up here. That's it
跳上来呀
You can do it. Come on. Come on!
你是神犬，没问题
Put some effort into it!
用力跳
Baby, there you are
宝贝，总算找到你了
I was worried about you
我不大放心你
- You talk to the cops? - Only to see what Ipkiss told them
你找条子告密？ 我只有问伊卜吉的事
That's right, you and Stanley. You two are getting awfully close
你跟他走得太近了吧
Bet you helped him with the bank job
他抢银行想必是你帮他
- That's ridiculous. - Oh, is it?
胡说 是吗？
Look what I found in her car
她车上有行李
Going away alone, baby?
想一个人溜吗？
Boys, I want you to...
喽罗们
get her something pretty to wear
给她找件漂亮衣服
We're going to a party tonight
今晚有宴会
We'll have one hell of a time, right?
要痛快飙一晚
Get out of my sight
你滚一边去
Jump up
跳呀
Get up. Come on
百尺竿头，更进一步
Come on, Milo. Jump, please
麦乐，拜托你跳
Do it for Daddy
为你老子跳一个
That's it!
酷呆了
God, I can't believe it
真想不到
Good boy. Good boy
我的乖孩子
See that man over there?
看到那个人吗？
He's got keys
他有钥匙
Go get those keys
把钥匙弄来
Go get them. Go get the keys
去偷钥匙
That's it
对了
The key
钥匙
No, not the cheese, the keys
不是起司，是钥匙
Drop the cheese...
放下起司
and get the keys
去偷钥匙
Over there, over there
在那边
Oh, man. Come on
乖狗儿，过来
Come here. Good boy. That's a good boy
我的好祖宗
Give it, give me the keys. Give me the keys
把钥匙给我
Come on, drop it, drop it
松口啦
It's sundown
太阳下山了
It's almost time
好戏开锣了
I wouldn't, darling
我劝你别点烟
DANGER EXPLOSIVES
（炸药，危险）
Wouldn't want to start the celebration early
别这么早放烟火
Hold it!
不要动
I am warning you...
我警告你
I am seriously stressed out here
你逼得我要发飙了
Easy
放轻松
Come on
过来
Don't be an idiot
别活得不耐烦
You're in a police station. There is no way you'll walk out of here like this
这里是警察局 你不可能出得去
You're know, you're right
你说得对
- Absolutely right. - What are you doing?
一点也没错 你干什么？
You'll take me out...
咱们玩...
as your prisoner
官兵抓强盗
Put it on! Put it on!
铐上！
Come on
走
- I'm really very sorry about this. - I'm sure
我很遗憾
You got the wrong guy
你们抓错人了
It's a bum rap
我是冤大头
I got my rights
要尊重人权嘛
Where are you taking Ipkiss?
你为何带走伊卜吉？
Ixnay! Ehay's otgay an ungay
“枪有他”
I get it. Pig Latin, right?
原来你倒过来讲
Eesay ouyay aterlay
“见头回”
Come on!
来呀
Sit back and relax
你坐好，放轻松
I must change for the party
我要更衣赴宴
TONIGHT, CASINO
“豪睹之夜”
WAR ORPHANS FUND
“战火孤儿基金”
I need cigarettes
买烟
- Which brand? - It doesn't matter, I don't smoke
什么牌子？ 无所谓，我不抽烟
But for you, I would shoot the Surgeon General
但我会帮你杀掉卫生署长
Mayor Tilton, may we have a word?
条顿市长，可以访问您吗？
I always have time for the press and my loyal constituents
我一向 欢迎新闻界和忠心选民
Let me out of these cuffs, you drive like a maniac
放开我，你开车太恐怖
Sorry, we're late for the ball
抱歉，怕赶不上舞会
Alice and the rabbit'll be disappointed
别假仙了，迟到大王
Now you're being cynical
你也会讽刺了
Who are you?
你是谁？
I'm just an ex-employee...
我是你的离职员工
who's come for his back pay
我来讨你欠的薪水
Or should I say payback?
或者说来找你算帐
Kill him
杀掉他
Come on
你上呀
Ladies and gentlemen...
各位来宾
I will be the host...
现在起
for the rest of the evening
由我来主持
Get your dog away from me
拉开你的狗
Sorry, he seems to be attracted to you
它似乎和你心心相印
Where's everyone? Something's not kosher
人呢？情况不大妙
- Exactly. - Watch it!
小心
Sorry
对不起
I must lock you in
我必须把你锁在车内
Use the radio
打开无线电
You know, call for back-up or something
做什么？ 请求支援呀
This could be dangerous. Stay here and be a good boy
这很危险，你乖乖别动
Daddy has to go kick some ass
你老子我要去扁人
He's a dead man
他嫌人生乏味
Down! Get down!
趴下
Take it easy, I got the point
我懂，轻一点
Blow it!
轰掉它！
Bastard
你卑鄙
What's the matter, darling?
怎么了，亲爱的？
This is your big production number
他们是你的大舞群
And you know it's important...
做秀就是为了
to go out with a big bang
“轰轰烈烈”地成名
Why are you here?
查理，你怎么来了？
Take this gun and start sneaking people out the back
拿着枪，溜到后面去
Step back
退后
- Do you know who I am? - A dead man if you don't step back
你知道我是什么人？ 你不退后就是死人
What about some respect?
你难道不尊重法律和命令吗？
- What kind of thug are you? - All set, Dorian
你算什么流氓呀？ 炸弹设定完毕
That's it
好极了
This party's over...
再过十分钟
in 10 minutes
舞会就完了
This is the moment when a man...
在这一关键时刻
shows what he's really made of
男儿要展露本性
Crap
枪放下
Drop it
放下
Smart dog
真机灵
Boss, look who decided to crash the party
老板，有不速之客
How's it going?
多利安，你好吗？
Bring him up here!
带过来！
Wait! No!
多利安，等一下
This is no time for last requests
没时间听你的临终请求
But all I wanted was a kiss
我只求一吻
A kiss?
一个吻？
Just one...
只是一个吻...
last kiss
最后的一吻
I can't shut it off
定时器关不掉呀
There's always time...
有的是时间
for one last kiss
才一个吻而已
From the real Dorian
要正牌的多利安来吻
The one I used to love
我所爱的那位
Nobody ever kissed me like Dorian Tyrel
他的吻举世无双
Romeo!
罗密欧呀
This place will blow!
这儿快炸了
Just wait!
你给我等着！
I've decided...
我决定了
to give her one last thrill
我要让她含笑而终
Get it!
接住它！
Run, Milo!
快跑，麦乐
Stanley, hurry!
史丹利，快呀
Don't worry
你安啦
It's all over now
已经没戏唱了
Got you
抓住你了
I'll take you apart
我要剥你的皮
I hope you can enjoy the victory with one freaking eye!
用你的独眼享受胜利吧
Good doggie
狗儿乖乖
I'm winning!
我赢了！
JACKPOT
我是洛基！
Oh, my God!
我的老天呀！
This must be a new breed
它一定是新品种
Easy, boy!
别急
Good boy!
好狗儿
Did you miss me?
你们又没打中吗？
I guess not!
打中了
Now, you have to ask yourself one question:
你们快扪心自问：
"Do I feel Iucky?"
“我的命够硬吗？”
Well...
怎样呀？
do you...
痞子，你们的够硬吗？
punks?
（玩具枪）
That's a spicy meatball
这肉丸挺辣的
How do?
怎样呀？
This guy's incorrigible
这家伙狗命真长
You were good, kid, real good...
你是很有两下子啦
but as long as I'm around you'll be second-best
但只要有我 你就一边凉快
Police! Hands up!
手举起来！
Officers, arrest those men
条子们，逮捕这些人！
I've always wanted to say that
指挥警察真神气
Come on
走
Give me that gun
枪拿来
He stole all our jewelry. Take me to headquarters...
他抢了我们的珠宝
Stop that man!
拦住他
I've got you now
伊卜吉，我逮到你了
Watch it, Chunky!
小心，死胖子
- Mayor Tilton, I'm so-- - What's wrong with you?
真抱歉，条顿市长 你搞什么鸟龙？
That man is The Mask
他就是面具怪客
No. Dorian Tyrel was The Mask. I saw it with my own eyes
多利安才是 我亲眼看见
This man here saved our lives
他是我们的救星
- With a little help. - You're a real hero
有我相助嘛 你真是英雄
It's nothing...
这没什么
any American with...
身为铁血美国男儿
balls of steel wouldn't do for his community
愿为社会贡献一切
Come on
麦乐，走
Mayor Tilton, did you see that dog?
市长，你看到那只狗？
Leave the dog alone
你少去惹它
I want you in my office first thing tomorrow
明天一大早找我报到
- Yes, Your Honor. - That doesn't sound good at all
是，大人 拍马屁没用啦
No, it doesn't. What would sound good to you?
是没用，你说什么才有用？
- Breakfast. - Shut up!
吃早饭 闭嘴
Sure you know what you're doing?
你确定要这样做？
I'm sure
我确定
Then do what you must
那就动手吧
Sure you won't miss this guy?
你真的不会怀念他？
When he's gone, all that's left is me
他走了，就只剩下我
Smoking!
甜到心坎里！